Finding Aid for I. Leo Sharfman papers, 1914-1962
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
I. Leo. Sharfman papers 1914-1962
Sharfman, I. Leo (Isaiah Leo), 1886-
8656 Aa 2
Professor of economics at University of Michigan, referee with National Railroad Adjustment Board, member and chairman of various emergency and arbitration boards under Railroad Labor Act. Professional papers largely concerning his work toward the settlement of labor disputes, the publication of his books, his work on establishing a Zionist movement in Michigan, 1914-1918, especially in correspondence with Louis D. Brandeis and Horace M. Kallen; and photographs.
11 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The bulk of the collection came from Professor Sharfman (donor no. 1035 )
No further additions to the records are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Isaiah Leo Sharfman was born in Polonnoe, Ukraine, Russia, February 19, 1886. He came to the United States in 1894 and became a citizen by virtue of his father's naturalization on November 30, 1903. Sharfman graduated from the Boston Latin School in 1904, received the A.B. degree from Harvard College in 1904, and an LL.B. degree from the Harvard Law School in 1910. During the two academic years 1908-10 he was assistant in economics at Harvard.
Sharfman was admitted to the Massachusetts Bar in 1909. He was professor of law and political science at the Imperial Pei-Yang University, at Tientsin, China, in 1910 and 1911, and he was chief investigator of Commission Regulation of Public Utilities for the National Civic Foundation, in 1912.
He came to The University of Michigan in 1912, where he has been, successively, lecturer in economics (1912-13), associate professor (1913-14), professor (1914-55), Henry Carter Adams University Professor (1947-55), and chairman of the Department of Economics (1927-54). In 1939 he was visiting professor of economics at Stanford University, and since 1955 he has been a member of the Board of Trustees of Brandeis University.
Sharfman has been director of an investigation of Anti-Trust Policy for the National Industrial Conference Board (1923-24); a member of the Board of Editors of the American Economic Review (1929-31); a member of the Advisory Committee on Railroad Employment to the Federal Coordinator of Transportation (1933-35); a member of the Advisory Committee on Economists and Social Scientists to the President's Committee on Civil Service Improvement (1939); an associate public member of the National War Labor Board (1942-44); an associate public member of the National Railway Labor Panel (1943-46); a member of the Editorial Board of the Petroleum Monograph Series (1949-59); and since 1936 he has served, intermittently, as referee for the National Railroad Adjustment Board, as a member and chairman of Presidential Emergency Boards, and as a member and chairman of Ad Hoc Arbitration Boards -- all under the Railway Labor Act.
In 1939 Sharfman was awarded the James Barr Ames Prize for legal writing by the Faculty of the Harvard Law School; In 1965 he was selected Distinguished Fellow of the American Economic Association; In 1943 he was Henry Russel Lecturer at The University of Michigan; In 1945 he was President of the American Economic Association; in 1954 he was President of the Michigan Academy of Science, Arts and Letters.
He is the author of Railway Regulation, 1915, The American Railroad Problem, 1921, The Interstate Commerce Commission, 1931-37 (five volumes), and of contributions to economic and legal journals and to the Encyclopedia of the Social Sciences.
The Sharfman papers have been arranged into the following series: Correspondence; Professional activities; Writings; Addresses and Lectures; Other activities and interests; and University of Michigan.
Subjects:
Jews--Michigan.; Railroads--Employees--Labor unions.; Menorah Association (New York, N.Y.); Railroads--United States.; Strikes and lockouts--Railroads.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Economics.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; Zionism.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Sharfman, I. Leo (Isaiah Leo), 1886-1969
Subjects - Sound Recordings:
University of Michigan. Dept. of Economics.; Ackley, Gardner.; Boulding, Kenneth E. (Kenneth Ewart), 1910-1993
Contributors:
Brandeis, Louis Dembitz, 1856-1941.; Day, Edmund Ezra, 1883-1951.; Douglas, Paul H. (Paul Howard), 1892-1976; Frankfurter, Felix, 1882-1965.; Galbraith, John Kenneth, 1908-2006.; Harris, Seymour Edwin, 1897-1974.; Janeway, Eliot.; Kallen, Horace Meyer, 1882-1974.; Lubin, Isador, 1896-1978; Myrdal, Gunnar, 1898-1987.; Perlman, Selig, 1888-1959; Roosevelt, Franklin D. (Franklin Delano), 1882-1945.; Schumpeter, Joseph Alois, 1883-1950.; Slichter, Sumner H. (Sumner Huber), 1892-1959.; Taussig, F. W. (Frank William), 1859-1940.; Truman, Harry S., 1884-1972.; Vinson, Fred M., 1890-1953.; Wallace, Henry Agard, 1888-1965.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.; Sound recordings.
- Correspondence
  - Abramson, Victor (Box 1)
  - Adams, James Pickwell (Box 1)
  - Amrod, Charles (Box 1)
  - Anderson, Benjamin M. (Box 1)
  - Angell, James W. (Box 1)
  - Ayres, Clarence (Box 1)
  - Ayres, Leonard P. (Box 1)
  - Bach, G.L. (Box 1)
  - Barnes, Irston R (Box 1)
  - Beckerath, Herbert von (Box 1)
  - Belfer, Nathan (Box 1)
  - Bell, James W.I., 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Belshaw, Horace (Box 1)
  - Bergson, Abram (Box 1)
  - Berridge, William A. (Box 1)
  - Blodgett, Ralph H. (Box 1)
  - Boddy, Francis M. (Box 1)
  - Bogart, Ernest L. (Box 1)
  - Bonebright, James C. (Box 1)
  - Bortz, Nelson M. (Box 1)
  - Brandeis, Louis D. (Box 1)
  - Brown, J. Douglas (Box 1)
  - Bryce, Robert B. (Box 1)
  - Buchanan, Norman S. (Box 1)
  - Burgess, Edwin H. (Box 1)
  - Burns, Arthur R. (Box 1)
  - Burns, Eveline (Box 1)
  - Burton, Marion Leroy (Box 1)
  - Calkins, Robert D. (Box 1)
  - Clark, T.M. (Box 1)
  - Clayton, William L. (Box 1)
  - Clemens, E.W. (Box 1)
  - Cole, Arthur H. (Box 1)
  - Connable, Alfred B. (Box 1)
  - Cox, Garfield V. (Box 1)
  - Crow, Allen B. (Box 1)
  - Crum, William L. (Box 1)
  - Davis, Joseph S. (Box 1)
  - Day, Edmund Ezra (Box 1)
  - de Chazeau, Melvin G (Box 1)
  - Deimel, Henry L. (Box 1)
  - Dewhurst, J. Frederic (Box 1)
  - Diebold, William (Box 1)
  - Dimock, Marshall F. (Box 1)
  - Dodd, Dean Paul A. (Box 1)
  - Donaldson, John (Box 1)
  - Domar, Evsey D. (Box 1)
  - Douglas, Paul H. (Box 1)
  - Edminster, Lynn R. (Box 1)
  - Edwards, Corwin D. (Box 1)
  - Ellis, David M. (Box 1)
  - Ellis, Howard S. (Box 1)
  - Ellsworth, Paul T. (Box 1)
  - Epstein, Ralph C. (Box 1)
  - Estey, James A. (Box 1)
  - Evans, George H. (Box 1)
  - Ezekiel, Mordecai (Box 1)
  - Fellner, William J. (Box 1)
  - Fetter, Frank A., 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Fisher, Clyde O. (Box 1)
  - Fisher, Irving (Box 1)
  - Fisher, Walter (Box 1)
  - Fitch, John A. (Box 2)
  - Fournier, Leslie T. (Box 2)
  - Frankfurter, Felix (Box 2)
  - Friday, David (Box 2)
  - Galbraith, John K. (Box 2)
  - Gilbert, Milton (Box 2)
  - Glasser, Martin G. (Box 2)
  - Goldstein, Emanuel A. (Box 2)
  - Grady, Henry F. (Box 2)
  - Grether, Ewald T. (Box 2)
  - Groves, Harold M. (Box 2)
  - Haley, Bernard F. (Box 2)
  - Hallett, Ralph H. (Box 2)
  - Hamilton, Earl J. (Box 2)
  - Harbezon, Robert W. (Box 2)
  - Hardy, Charles O. (Box 2)
  - Harris, Abram L. (Box 2)
  - Harris, Basil (Box 2)
  - Harris, Seymour E. (Box 2)
  - Hart, Albert G. (Box 2)
  - Hatcher, Harlan (Box 2)
  - Heatherington, Donald F. (Box 2)
  - Hefflebower, Richard B. (Box 2)
  - Heilperin, Michael A. (Box 2)
  - Homan, Paul T. (Box 2)
  - Hoover, Calvin B. (Box 2)
  - Horn, Paul V. (Box 2)
  - Humphrey, Don D. (Box 2)
  - Hunsberger, Warren S. (Box 2)
  - Hutchins, John C.B. (Box 2)
  - Innis, Harold A. (Box 2)
  - Janeway, Eliot (Box 2)
  - Jones, Eliot (Box 2)
  - Kallen, Horace M. (Box 2)
  - Keezer, Dexter M. (Box 2)
  - Kline, Chester A. (Box 2)
  - Koontz, Harold D. (Box 2)
  - Koopmans, Tjalling C. (Box 2)
  - Kuznets, Simon (Box 2)
  - Leiserson, William M. (Box 2)
  - Leland, Simeon E. (Box 2)
  - Lerner, Abba P. (Box 2)
  - Lester, Richard A. (Box 2)
  - Lindeman, Edward C. (Box 2)
  - Livermore, Shaw (Box 2)
  - Lockhart, Oliver C. (Box 2)
  - Locklin, D. Phillip (Box 2)
  - Lubin, Isador, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - McFarland, Walter (Box 2)
  - Machlup, Fritz (Box 2)
  - Marx, Daniel (Box 2)
  - Mason, Edward S. (Box 2)
  - May, Stacy (Box 2)
  - McIssac, Archibald M. (Box 2)
  - McLaughlin, Glenn E. (Box 2)
  - Means, Gardiner C. (Box 2)
  - Metzler, Lloyd A. (Box 2)
  - Meyer, Balthasar H. (Box 2)
  - Miller, Sidney L. (Box 2)
  - Millis, Harry A. (Box 2)
  - Mills, Frederick G. (Box 2)
  - More, Joseph (Box 2)
  - Morehouse, Edward W. (Box 2)
  - Morgan, Charles S. (Box 2)
  - Morganstern, Oskar (Box 2)
  - Moulton, Harold G. (Box 2)
  - Murphy, Mary E. (Box 2)
  - Myrdal, Gunnar (Box 2)
  - Nelson, James C. (Box 2)
  - Newcomer, Mabel (Box 2)
  - Northrup, Herbert R. (Box 2)
  - Nourse, Edwin G. (Box 2)
  - Nurske, Ragnar (Box 2)
  - Orchard, John E. (Box 2)
  - Overton, Richard C. (Box 2)
  - Patchin, Robert H. (Box 2)
  - Patterson, Howard S. (Box 2)
  - Patton, Harold Smith (Box 2)
  - Pegrum, Dudley F. (Box 2)
  - Perlman, Selig (Box 2)
  - Perry, Hobart S. (Box 2)
  - Pierson, John H.G. (Box 2)
  - Preston, Howard H. (Box 2)
  - Radvanyi, Laszlo (Box 2)
  - Reynolds, Lloyd G. (Box 3)
  - Riefler, Winfield (Box 3)
  - Roosevelt, Franklin D. (Box 3)
  - Rosenthal, Morris S. (Box 3)
  - Rosenthal, Samuel R. 1921-1967, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Ross, Arthur (Box 3)
  - Roth, Almon E. (Box 3)
  - Ruggles, Clyde O. (Box 3)
  - Ruthven, Alexander G. (Box 3)
  - Sachs, Alexander (Box 3)
  - Schell, Samuel D. (Box 3)
  - Schultz, Theodore W. (Box 3)
  - Schumpeter, Joseph A. (Box 3)
  - Seymour, Walton (Box 3)
  - Shoup, Carl S. (Box 3)
  - Simons, Henry C. (Box 3)
  - Slichter, Sumner H. (Box 3)
  - Smith, Elmer A. (Box 3)
  - Smith, Nelson Lee (Box 3)
  - Shell, Hampton K. (Box 3)
  - Spengler, Joseph J. (Box 3)
  - Staley, A. Eugene (Box 3)
  - Starr, Mark (Box 3)
  - Stevens, William H.S. (Box 3)
  - Stewart, W. Blair (Box 3)
  - Stocking, George W. (Box 3)
  - Sumner, John D. (Box 3)
  - Sweezy, Alan R. (Box 3)
  - Tamagna, Frank M. (Box 3)
  - Taussig, F.W. (Box 3)
  - Taylor, Alonzo E. (Box 3)
  - Taylor, George (Box 3)
  - Taylor, Horace (Box 3)
  - Terborgh, George W. (Box 3)
  - Troxel, Emery (Box 3)
  - Truman, Harry (Box 3)
  - Viner, Jacob (Box 3)
  - Vinson, Fred (Box 3)
  - Volin, Lazar (Box 3)
  - Wallace, Donald H. (Box 3)
  - Warburton, Clark A. (Box 3)
  - Watkins, Myron W. (Box 3)
  - Wickens, Aryness J. (Box 3)
  - Willcox, Walter F. (Box 3)
  - Williams, John H. (Box 3)
  - Willits, Joseph H. (Box 3)
  - Wilson, G. Lloyd (Box 3)
  - Witte, Edwin E. (Box 3)
  - Wolfe, Albert B. (Box 3)
  - Woodward, Donald B. (Box 3)
  - Working, Elmer J. (Box 3)
  - Wright, David M. (Box 3)
  - Wubnig, Arthur (Box 3)
  - Wyatt, Harry N. (Box 3)
  - Young, Donald (Box 3)
  - Young, Ralph (Box 3)
- Professional activities
  - National Railroad Adjustment Board
    - First Division 1936-1951 (Box 4)
    - Second Division 1936-1951 (Box 4)
    - Third Division 1936-1941 (Box 4)
    - Fourth Division 1940-1951 (Box 4)
    - Referee decisions 1936-1940 (Box 4)
  - Emergency Board Files
    - Clerks, Longshoremen and N.Y. Railroads 1937 (Box 4)
    - Pacific Electric and Trainmen 1937 (Box 4)
    - Rutland Railroad and Fifteen Organizations 1941, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Non-operating employees, wage increase and Union Shop 1943 (Box 4)
    - Operating Employees Wage Increase 1943 (Box 4)
    - Finances (Box 4)
    - Clippings 1943 (Box 4)
    - Railroad Wage Cases, Final agreements 1943-1944 (Box 4)
    - Steelton and Highspire-Firemen and Trainmen 1944 (Box 5)
    - Teamsters Railway Express 1945 (Box 5)
    - Clerks-Railway Express 1946 (Box 5)
    - Pullman Conductors case
      - 1946 (Box 5)
      - 1950 (Box 5)
      - 1950 (report) (Box 5)
    - TWA Flight Engineers 1952 (Box 5)
    - Northwest Airlines 1952 (Box 5)
  - Arbitration Board files
    - General Motors and UAW 1939 (Box 5)
    - TWA and airline pilots 1941 (Box 5)
    - Railway Express Agency and Teamsters 1941 (Box 5)
    - Vacation dispute, Detroit, Toledo and Ironton Railroad Co. 1944, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Southern Pacific Co. and Locomotive engineers 1944 (Box 5)
    - Denver and Rio Grande Western Railroad Company 1945 (Box 5)
    - Kaiser-Frazer Corp. and Local 142 UAW 1948 (Box 6)
    - Detroit, Toledo and Ironton Railroad Company 1952 (Box 6)
  - National War Labor Board 1942-1943 (Box 6)
  - Regional War Labor Board 1943 (Box 6)
  - Michigan Labor Mediation Board (Box 6)
  - Federal Mediation and Conciliation Service 1952-1955 (Box 6)
  - President's Committee on Civil Service Improvement 1939-1941 (Box 6)
  - National Electric Light Association Committee on Cooperation with Educational Institutions 1927-1929, 3 folders (Box 6)
  - Lexington Group (railway history organization), Northwestern University 1944-1962 (Box 6)
  - Committee on Railroad Employment circa 1930s (Box 6)
  - Advisory Committee on Railroad Employment, Federal Coordinator of Transportation 1933-1936 (Box 6)
  - Interstate Commerce Commission (mainly relating to Sharfman's book The Interstate Commerce Commission; A Study in Administrative Law and Procedure)
    - Preliminary memoranda (Box 6)
    - Correspondence 1914-1956 (Box 6)
    - Yale Law Review comments, "The ICC: an appraisal" 1936-1937 (Box 7)
    - Comments and Reviews of "The Interstate Commerce Commission", 5 folders (Box 7)
    - Commonwealth Fund and publication of "The Interstate Commerce Commission"
      - George Welwood Murray (Box 7)
      - Max Farrand (Box 7)
      - Barry C. Smith (Box 7)
      - Graham Taylor (Box 7)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 7)
    - Potential appointment of Sharfman to fill vacancy on Interstate Commerce Commission 1941 (Box 7)
    - The Interstate Commerce Commission; A Study in Administrative Law and Procedure by I. L. Sharfman, 5 volumes (Box 7)
      (Gift of Samuel Rosenthal and coming through the President's Office, June 1982)
  - National Industrial Conference Board 1923-1924, 3 folders (Box 8)
  - American Economic Association
    - Transportation Round Table 1935-1936 (Box 8)
    - Committee on Consensus Reports (Box 8)
    - Conference miscellanea 1945-1946 (Box 8)
    - Presidential address of Sharfman, Cleveland, Ohio entitled "Law and Economics" and related 1946 (Box 8)
    - Committee on Honors and Awards 1946-1952, 4 folders (Box 8)
    - Nominations committee 1947 (Box 8)
    - Committee on Academic freedom 1948-1956 (Box 8)
    - Committee on Graduate training in economics 1950-1953 (Box 8)
    - Miscellanea 1914-1958 (Box 8)
  - American Arbitration Association 1941-1956 (Box 8)
- Writings
  - Introduction to American Law by I.L. Sharfman (papers relating to), 1913 (Box 8)
  - Appleton-Century Publishing Company correspondence 1919-1938 (Box 8)
  - "The American Railway Problem," 1921 by I.L. Sharfman (comments and review), 1921-1934 (Box 8)
  - American Economic Review (papers concerning), 1929-1958 (Box 8)
  - Encyclopedia of the Social Sciences
    - Correspondence 1927-1934 (Box 9)
    - Articles (Box 9)
  - "Transportation policy and the Railroads," 1938 (Box 9)
  - Contribution to Fortune transportation roundtable (Box 9)
  - "Free Enterprise, collective Bargaining, and the Arbitration Expedient," 1951 (Box 9)
  - Editorial board, Yale University and monograph series on petroleum industry 1949-1958 (Box 9)
  - LaSalle Extension University, largely concerning monograph Railway Regulation 1913-1927 (Box 9)
  - Miscellaneous periodical contributions, 2 folders (Box 9)
- Addresses and Lectures
  - Des Moines, Iowa 1936: "Economic control, the constitution and the Supreme Court" (Box 9)
  - Academy of Political Science 1938: "The Element of a Railroad program" (Box 9)
  - Commonwealth Club, San Francisco 1939: "Government by Commissions" (Box 9)
  - National Broadcasting Company, New York 1941 contribution by I.L. Sharfman to "Why Strikes in Defense Industry" (Box 9)
  - University of Michigan 1943, commencement address, "The Challenge of the World Crisis," (Box 9)
  - University of Michigan 1950, Law School Institute, contribution by I.L. Sharfman to "The Law and Labor Management Relations" (Box 9)
  - East Lansing, Mich. Economic Club of Southwestern Michigan 1952: "Regimentation, Centralization and Bureaucracy" (Box 9)
  - Miscellaneous addresses and lectures, 3 folders (Box 9)
  - University of Michigan Extension Division 1926-1932 (Box 10)
  - Extension lectures 1917-1936, 2 folders (Box 10)
- Other activities and interests
  - Zeta Beta Tau fraternity 1914-1951, 2 folders (Box 10)
  - Menorah Association (for the advancement and study of Jewish culture and ideas, 3 folders (Box 10)
  - Intercollegiate Intelligence Bureau 1917 (Box 10)
  - Association of Intercollegiate Schools of Business 1921 (Box 10)
  - American Institute of Banking 1922-1923 (Box 10)
  - American Association for Labor Legislation 1927-1928 (Box 10)
  - The American Foundation 1927-1929 (Box 10)
  - Public Utilities Reports, Inc. 1927-1930 (Box 10)
  - Social Science Research Council
    - Advisory Committee on Corporate Relations 1927-1930 (Box 10)
    - Committee on Scientific publications 1930-1931 (Box 10)
    - Miscellanea 1930-1932 (Box 10)
  - National Bureau of Economic Research 1938 (Box 10)
  - U.S. Armed Forces Institute 1946 (Box 10)
- University of Michigan
  - Appointment of I.L. Sharfman as chairman of Department of Economics at the University of Michigan 1928 (Box 11)
  - Appointment as Henry Carter Adams Professor of Economics at the University of Michigan 1947 (Box 11)
  - Reports on doctoral dissertations (Box 11)
  - Recommendations (Box 11)
  - University of Michigan School of Religion 1920 (Box 11)
  - Henry Carter Adams 1921-1922 (Box 11)
  - Award of James Barr Ames prize (Harvard Law School) to I.L. Sharfman 1939 (Box 11)
  - University of Michigan American Culture Institute lectures 1940 (Box 11)
  - University of Michigan Quadrangle lectures 1940-1941 (Box 11)
  - University of Michigan Henry Russel lectures 1943-1962 (Box 11)
    (Sharfman had received honor in 1943)
  - University of Michigan William Cook lectures 1943-1953 (Box 11)
  - University of Michigan committees 1927-1928 (Box 11)
  - University of Michigan Senate Committee on Retirement 1948 (Box 11)
  - Deanship of L.S.A. 1950-1952 (Box 11)
  - 25th anniversary dinner for I.L. Sharfman 1938 (Box 11)
  - I.L. Sharfman Fellowship Fund 1956-1962 (Box 11)
  - Opera 1953 "Ileolanthe" presented on occasion of retirement, also includes sound recording (Box 11)
  - Photographs (Box 11)